Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Association records, 1839-1995 MVC0049.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Association Records
1839-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0049.MS
6 Linear Feet
This collection contains publications, photographs, administration records and realia created and maintained by the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Association. Dating between 1889 and 1995, the publications include The Roll Call, Alumnae Roll Call, The Alumnae Asosociation of Mount Vernon Seminary, and Annual Reports of the Alumnae Association. The Alumnae Association was established in 1885 and merged with the Mount Vernon Seminary Society in 1933 to form the Mount Vernon Seminary Alumnae Association. Common topics discussed in the publications include campus and alumnae events, reunions, commencements, enrollment statistics, chapter news, Founder's Day, essays, personals, and updates on campus.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999.
The Alumnae Association of Mount Vernon seminary was established in 1885. Miss Minnie E. Naylor from the school's first class and Miss Frances C. Scoville from the class of 1884 wanted to form an organization that would reunite alumnae with each other and bind them to their alma mater. A group of previous students met in 1885 to establish a constitution, which included an annual reunion to be held the Saturday before commencement every June. By 1889, the Association boasted a membership of 90 alumnae, who each paid an annual fee of $1.00. Membership fees included the receipt of the Annual Report of the Alumnae Association.
The Mount Vernon Seminary Society was formed in 1905 as a means of binding together all of the pupils of the school, both graduates and undergraduates. Many of their efforts to draw the M.V.S. community together was through philanthropic educational work for children. Dues were $1.00/year, which included the annual receipt of their publication, The Roll Call. The difference between the Alumnae Association and the Mount Vernon Seminary Society was the inclusion of non-graduates. The Alumnae Association only allowed graduates to join; however, the Mount Vernon Seminary Society allowed anyone who had taken classes and faculty to join as well.
At a meeting in 1932, the Mount Vernon Seminary Society expressed a desire for the Alumnae Association to open to non-graduates. They wished for the word 'alumna' to include both graduate and non-graduate members. Additonally, the group also expressed their interest in combining the Alumnae Annual and The Roll Call because they felt that the two groups should work together as one common body of alumnae. On November 4, 1933 the two organizations merged to form The Mount Vernon Seminary Alumnae Association. As a result, their annual publications, The Roll Call and Alumnae Annual, were combined into the Alumnae Roll Call.
Conditions Governing Access Note
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement Note
Organized into four series: Publications, Photographs, Administrative records, and Realia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection contains the publications, photographs, administrative records, and realia of the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Association. The material dates from 1839 to 1995. Publications include theAnnual Reports of the Alumnae Association dating from 1889 to 1933; The Roll Call dates from 1913 to 1933; Alumnae Roll Call dates from 1934 to 1940; and the The Alumnae Asosociation of Mount Vernon Seminary was only published for one year, 1933. Other publications are also present. Materials contain information on campus life, Mount Vernon Seminary Council, meetings, alumnae reunions and luncheons, legacy daughters and granddaughters, reports on the treasury, marriages, briths, engagements, deaths, memorials, faculty and alumnae personals, lists of members, chapter news, school notes, Founder's Day, faculty notes, and M.V.S Day celebrations.
The photographs depict reunions, sporting events, personnel, and Washington DC in print, slide, and positive formats. The photographs date between 1976-1990 but many are undated. The administrative records date from 1989-1991 and detail the activities of the alumnae association, including reunions, budgets, sporting events, ledgers, and chapter information. Realia includes medals, songbooks, pins, and rings. They date between 1839-1975 and originate from academic and non-academic organizations within Mount Vernon College and Seminary.
Existence and Location of Copies Note
A complete set of Annual Reports of the Alumnae Association is available in the Special Collections Research Center reading room.
Alumni & alumnae; Women -- Education; Publications; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Publications, 1889-1995; Series 1; 3.5 Linear Feet 7 document boxes (Box 6, Box 7, Box 2, Box 1, Box 4, Box 3, Box 5)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains three publications by the Alumnae Association of Mount Vernon Seminary. Subseries 1 includes The Roll Call (1913-1933) and the Alumnae Roll Call (1934-1940). Subseries 2 contains Annual Reports of the Alumnae Association (1889-1933). The series also has one publication titled The Alumnae Association of Mount Vernon Seminary, which was only published for the academic year 1933-1934. Publications covered campus and alumnae topics such as reunions, commencements, enrollment statistics, chapter news, Founder's Day, essays, personals, and updates on campus for the purpose of creating a bond between alumnae and their alma mater.
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Alumnae Roll Call, Annual Reports of the Alumnae Association, and Publications.
  Women -- Education; Publications; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Alumnae Roll Call, 1913-1940; Series 1 Subseries 1
    The Roll Call debuted December 1913 as a yearly paper issued by the Mount Vernon Seminary Society. Published between 1913 and 1933, the paper was meant to connect any pupil of the school or member of the faculty, past or present, graduate or non-graduate. Topics include meetings, activities, campus updates, philanthropic efforts concerning children, a list of members, marriages, M.V.S. Society clubs, treasurer's reports, births, deaths, minutes, personals, school officers, M.V.S. Day celebrations, reunions, in memoriams, and various articles.
    When the Alumnae Association and Mount Vernon Seminary Society joined into a new organization—the Mount Vernon Seminary Alumnae Association—the annual publication changed its name to the Alumnae Roll Call. Publication dates from 1934 to 1940. The new publication took the place of The Roll Call and Annual Reports. Topics include M.V.S. Council meetings, commencement week, treasurer's reports, campus clubs, campus updates, essays, campus activities, books, enrollment statistics, births, deaths, marriages, engagements, in memoriams, chapter news, school notes, Founder's Day, faculty notes, personals, officers of the association and chapters, articles, and reunions. For the year 1940, issues were published for both Spring and Fall.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - The Roll Call, Vol. 1, No. 1-10, 1913-1923; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Roll Call, No. 4, December 1916; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Roll Call, Vol. 2, No. 11-20, 1923-1932; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Roll Call, No. 12, 1924; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Roll Call, No. 13, 1925; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The Roll Call, No. 15, 1927; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Roll Call, No. 18, 1930; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Roll Call, No. 19, 1931; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Roll Call, No. 20, 1932; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1934; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1935; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1936; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1937; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1938; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, 1939; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, Spring 1940; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, Fall 1940; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Alumnae Roll Call, Spring 1944; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports of the Alumnae Association, 1889; Series 1 Subseries 2
    Forty-five annual reports were published every June between 1889-1933. Publication ceased when the Alumnae Roll Call debuted in 1934. For the annual fee of $1.00, Mount Vernon Seminary alumnae could receive the annual report covering annual reunions, welcomes of the incoming class, essays, personals, updates on campus life, and in memoriams for deceased class members. As alumnae increased in numbers and dues increased to $2.00 per year, the contents of the annual reports expanded. By the time the last report was published in 1933, topics included a list of previous presidents, campus life updates, multiple essays, a section on the Mount Vernon Seminary Council, alumnae reunions and luncheons, legacy daughters and granddaughters, reports on the Alumane Association's treasury, marriages, births, deaths, memorials, faculty and alumnae personals, and a list of Alumnae Association members from each class.
    - 1st Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1889; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 2nd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1890; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 3rd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1891; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 4th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1892; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 5th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1893; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 6th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1894; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 7th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1895; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 8th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1896; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 9th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1897; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 10th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1898; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 11th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1899; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 12th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1900; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 13th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1901; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 14th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1902; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 15th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1903; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 16th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1904; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 17th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1905; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 18th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1906; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 19th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1907; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 20th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1908; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 21st Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1909; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 22nd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1910; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 23rd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1911; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 24th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1912; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 25th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1913; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 26th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1914; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 27th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1915; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 28th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1916; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 29th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1917; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 30th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1918; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 31st Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1919; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 32nd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1920; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 33rd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1921; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 34th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1922; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 35th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1923; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 36th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1924; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 37th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1925; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 38th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1926; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 39th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1927; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 40th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1928; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 41st Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1929; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 42nd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1930; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 43rd Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1931; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 44th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1932; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 45th Annual Report of the Alumnae Association, 1933; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1928-1995; Series 1 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains publications that did not have enough issues to warrant separate subseries. The publications include The Alumnae Association of Mount Vernon Seminary, which was only published for the academic year 1933-1934. Publications covered campus and alumnae topics such as reunions, commencements, enrollment statistics, chapter news, Founder's Day, essays, personals, and updates on campus for the purpose of creating a bond between alumnae and their alma mater.
    - The Alumnae Association of Mount Vernon Seminary, 1933-1934; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Directory and Creed, 1928; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - The Freedom Forum, 1995 September 28; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Mount Vernon College Bulletin (Vol. 31, No. 3), 1974; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Mount Vernon College Bulletin (Vol. 32, No. 1), 1975 June; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Mount Vernon Reunion Yearbook, 1990; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Seminary Songbook, undated; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - The Voice, 1994 September - October; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Washington Star: First 100 Years, 1952 December 16; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1976-1990; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet
  The series consists of photographs in print form, slides, and photographic positives. Most date between 1976-1990 and many are undated. The photographs depict events at Mount Vernon College and Seminary such as reuions, sporting events, and personnel. Images of the Washington, D.C. area are also included.
  Women -- Education; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Awards Week Fireside Chat, undated; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1940 Reunion, 1990; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Health Day, 1987; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Founders Day and Tennis Classic, 1987; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Library Construction, 1987; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Teen Leadership, 1987; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Tennis, undated; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Washington Area, undated; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - William J. Keller and Joseph Crilley (R37993), undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 4th of July, 1976; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Photographic Slides (1/2), 1990; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Photographic Slides (2/2), 1990; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Undated Photographic Positives, Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Undated Photographs, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Undated Photographs, Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Undated Photographs, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Undated Photographs, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Administrative Records, 1989-1991; Series 3; 1 Linear Feet
  The records consist of organizational materials, handbooks, and ledger books. The materials date between 1989-1991. The records pertain to the activities of the alumnae association including reunions, budgets, chapter information, and sporting events.
  - Alumni Administration, undated; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Association Minutes, 1947-1954; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Alumnae Task Force Meeting, 1988 September 23; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports of the Alumnae Office, 1959-1978; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Archives and Timeline, undated; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Budget, 1989-1991; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Chapter Organization and Profiles (1/2), 1989-1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Chapter Organization and Profiles (2/2), 1989-1990; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Council, 1969; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - General Ledger: Endowment Fund and Restricted Fund, 1945-1973; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder data_value_missing_bfb9f992fabd76010bfaf0ece138a336)
  - General Ledger: Endowment Fund and Restricted Fund, 1945-1973; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder data_value_missing_00ca025bce1659e49bcba33fc5e8b2fa)
  - General Ledger: Plant Fund, 1945-1973; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Notes, 1979-1987; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Olympic Torch, 1996; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Reunion, 1988 September 23-25; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Reunion, 1987; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Reunion (1/4), 1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Reunion (2/4), 1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Reunion (3/4), 1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Reunion (4/4), 1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Reunion Registration, 1989-1991; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Reunion Registration, 1992; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Special Collections Room Dedication, 1988 September 23; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Student Handbook, undated; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Tennis Classic, 1988; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Tennis Classic, 1988; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Tennis Classic (1/2), 1996; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Tennis Classic (2/2), 1996; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Washington DC Chapter - Annual Fund, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Washington DC Chapter - Event Attendees, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Washington DC Chapter - Participants, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Washington DC Chapter - Reunion Attendees, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Washington DC Chapter - Reunion Committee, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Realia, 1839-1975; Series 4; 1 Linear Feet 2 boxes
  The realia includes medals, songbooks, rings, a paperweight, and pins. The materials date from 1877-1975. The materials result from participation in school groups, class activities, religious groups, and non-academic organizations.
  - Dance Card with Pencil Attached, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 1)
  - Student Directory, 1916; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 2)
  - Student Directory, 1918; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 3)
  - Key to Case for Moving Pictures, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 4)
  - Class Songs Songbook, 1919; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 5)
  - Business Card Case, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 6)
  - Pencil, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 7)
  - Class Ring, 1950; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 8)
  - Omega Ring, 1934; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 9)
  - Class Ring, 1932; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 10)
  - Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 11)
  - Silver Cuff, 1909-1941; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 16, Object 12)
  - Paperweight, 1975; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 1)
  - Methodist Hymnal, 1839; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 2)
  - Court Club Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 3)
  - Fleur-de-lis Ring, 1939; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 4)
  - AX Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 5)
  - W Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 6)
  - Omega and Torch Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 7)
  - White MVS Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 8)
  - BTS Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 9)
  - First Honors Medal, 1877; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 10)
  - Plaque, 1937; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 11)
  - White ITS Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 12)
  - Black ITS Pin, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 13)
  - Medal, undated; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 17, Box 17, Object 14)